Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Community Center Records 1920s-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Community Center Records 1920s-1988
Ann Arbor Community Center
0.5 linear ft.
Organization established to promote civic, cultural, and recreational interests and activities of Ann Arbor's African American community. Administrative reports, informational brochures, collected information, and photographs.
00143 Bd 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were accessioned from the Center in February of 2000. Donor no. 6775.
The record group is open for research.
In 1923, the Reverend R.M. Gilbert, pastor of the Second Baptist Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan, spearheaded the effort that led to the establishment of the Dunbar Community Center. The original intent of the Center was to provide housing for Black laborers working on area roads and University of Michigan building projects. The Center's first building, located at 209-11 North Fourth Avenue, was used primarily for sleeping quarters, but there were also a few areas set aside for club meetings and social events. Gradually the purpose of the Center changed from one of providing temporary housing to that of being a place where Ann Arbor's Black population could gather for social, recreational, and civic activities.
In 1926, a new administrator, Mrs. Savonia L. Carson, was appointed Executive Secretary and the Center moved to 1009 East Catherine where it remained until 1937. That same year, Mr. Douglas Williams moved to Ann Arbor to assume the leadership of the Dunbar Center. Mr. Williams, although trained as a pharmacist, had a certificate from the Atlanta School of Social Work. His first priority was to reorganize and revitalize the Center who membership was then quite small. He quickly arranged for the purchase of a new facility at 420 North Fourth Avenue. He also set about revitalizing the programs -- and succeeded to such an extent that the membership in a very short time jumped from 57 to 371.
The constitution of the Center, under Williams' guidance, was revised and broadened to read as follows: "The purpose of the Association shall be to promote civic and cultural and recreational interest and activities to serve all ages and both sexes and to direct character building and community betterment programs among the colored citizens of Ann Arbor and its suburbs."
During the 1940's and 1950's, the program at the Dunbar Center was influenced to a large extent by the personality and interests of Mr. Williams. He was a member of innumerable organizations and performed many charitable works, both as a member of these groups and on a personal basis. Because of his influence, Blacks were given jobs previously reserved for white applicants. He sought to bring about good race relations and community harmony through his own good works and personal magnetism. Through Mr. Williams' efforts and close personal contacts, he was able to build a new modern Center at 625 N. Main St. Sometime in 1958, the name of the organization was changed to the Ann Arbor Community Center. Six months after the new building was dedicated in 1960, Mr. Williams died.
Mr. Walter W. Hill, who also completed his professional training at the Atlanta School of Social Work, became the next head of the center. In 1962, the Board stated its intention that Program development should be its major priority. Still relying primarily on volunteer staff in 1963, the Center developed a closer relationship with the University's School of Social Work for student placements.
In the early 1970s, the center began to hire part-time and then full-time professionally trained staff. In 1972, the Center purchased a former YM-YWCA Camp that provided summertime activities for Ann Arbor African-American youth.
By 1973, the staff included the Director, a Program Director, an Administrative Assistant, two social workers and five part-time program specialists. A custodian and receptionist-typist and eight Camp Counselors completed the staff.
While many activities continued at the Center, much staff time was spent in "reaching out" to youth in trouble in the schools and courts. Block clubs were established to help groups in the community develop civic pride and civic strength, which led to the establishment of the North Central Neighborhood Association.
Many programs developed in conjunction with other community groups. A program for "In School Mothers" and educational counseling was a joint effort of the center and school personnel. A bookmobile station at the Center was established with cooperation of the Library Advisory Committee. A program for school dropouts was established with the Human Rights Department. a Voter Education program with the City Clerk's office, and a transportation program with Model Cities.
The records of the Ann Arbor Community Center, spannig the period 19 linear feet document the Center's service to Ann Arbor's African-American community. The records, including annual reports, brochures, clippings and photographs have been arranged into three series: Administrative, 1936-1998; Topical, 1936-1997; and Visual, 1920s-1990s
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Community Center.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Race relations.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor Community Center.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Children--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Camps.; Children--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Community centers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administrative, 1936-1998
  The Administrative series spans less than 0.1 linear feet and includes materials pertaining primarily to the early years of the Center. Of particular note are Annual Reports of the Center (then the Dunbar Community Association) from 1937 to 1954, as well as Brochures, Fliers and Invitations regarding Center events and services from 1936 to 1998.
  - Annual Reports, Dunbar Community Association, 1937-1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures, Fliers and Invitations, 1936-1998, undated (Box 1)
  - Dedication Ceremony Program, January 24, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Expansion Proposal, "The Dunbar Story" (Box 1)
- Topical Files, 1936-1997
  The Topical series spans approximately 0.2 linear feet and includes materials kept by the Center on related organizations or individuals, as well as a considerable quantity of newspaper clippings relating to the Center itself.
  - Annual Report, Boys Department, St. Antoine Branch YMCA, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, Ann Arbor Civic Forum, 1950 (Box 1)
  - History, Second Baptist Church of Ann Arbor (Box 1)
  - Memorial Program, Douglas E. H. Williams, November 20, 1960 (Box 1)
  - News Clippings
    - From an album, 1978-1981, undated (Box 1)
      (include photocopy of newspaper photo of original Board of Directors)
    - General, 1941-1997, undated (Box 1)
- Visual, 1920s-1990s
  The Visual series spans approximately .3 linear feet and consists of negatives and photographs. The bulk of the photographs are undated, although there are a fair amount for which a date or date range was apparent. Of these, photographs of the 1940s, 1960s and 1970s are the most abundant.
  - Photographs
    - 1920s (Box 1)
    - 1940s (Box 1)
    - 1950s (Box 1)
    - 1960s (Box 1)
    - 1970s (Box 1)
    - 1980s-1990s, include some negatives (Box 1)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Negatives
    - 1930s (Box 1)
    - 1950s (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Postcards of Ann Arbor Community Center, undated (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook1936-1949, undated, (includes photographs and news clippings) (Box 1)